Guide to the Malcom 'Moki Mac' Ellingson river running video collection circa 1914 1956-1963
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Malcom 'Moki Mac' Ellingson river running video collection
circa 1914
1956-1963
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 801-581-8864 http://www.lib.utah.edu/collections/multimedia-archives/
A1022
Ellingson, Malcom
27 8mm films, 4 16mm films.
The Malcom 'Moki Mac' Ellingson river running video collection (circa 1914, 1956-1963) consists of home movies of river trips in southern Utah and the vicinity, most frequently in the Glen Canyon area of the Colorado River. Several films contain footage of Native American towns and customs. The earliest film in the collection is a 16mm copy of a 35mm nitrate, intertitled film of boat trips on the Colorado River circa 1914. The collection also includes some films of Ellingson's family and other life scenes. 'Moki Mac' Ellingson was a Boy Scout leader and guide on many river expeditions.
Biographical Note
Malcom 'Moki Mac' Ellingson was a prominent figure in Utah's river running community in the mid twentieth century. Boy Scout leader and river guide, Ellingson earned his nickname from his knowledge about the Moqui, prehistoric inhabitants of the Colorado Plateau and its river canyons. Ellingson partnered with Albert Quist in the early years of his river expedition company. Today Quist's children operate Moki Mac River Expeditions, named in his honor.
The Malcom 'Moki Mac' Ellingson river running video collection (circa 1914, 1956-1963) consists of home movies of river trips in southern Utah and the vicinity, most frequently in the Glen Canyon area of the Colorado River. Several films contain footage of Native American towns and customs. The earliest film in the collection is a 16mm copy of a 35mm nitrate, intertitled film of boat trips on the Colorado River circa 1914. The collection also includes some films of Ellingson's family and other life scenes. Item titles based largely on Ellingson's own labels. All materials have been digitized and are available to view on DVD.
Materials are arranged chronologically by format.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
Donate by Robert Quist in 2010.
Moki Mac River Expeditions; Utah; Arizona; New Mexico; Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico); Rivers--Recreational use; Native American life; Sports and Recreation; Moving Images; Moving images
- 8mm films, 1956-1963
  - River rafting in redrock country, 1956; 8mm film (Reel 1)
    River rafting in redrock country; man and boy in cowboy hats with guitar in city park; canoeing in forested area.
  - Canoeing (washed out), 1956; 8mm film (Reel 2)
    Canoeing (washed out); parade; cliff at Stanton.
  - Woman in red hat, 1956; 8mm film (Reel 3)
    Woman in red hat; dirt road from vehicle while driving, probably in Southern Utah.
  - Canoes (very dark), 1957; 8mm film (Reel 4)
    Canoes (very dark); flying in airplane.
  - Flying, 1957; 8mm film (Reel 5)
    Flying in airplane: shots of Utah National Guard hangar; shots from airplane taking off, in flight.
  - Flying, 1957; 8mm film (Reel 6)
    Shots out windows of airplane in flight.
  - Men on rafting trip, 1957; 8mm film (Reel 7)
    Men on rafting trip; scenery as seen from boat.
  - Parade with Native American dancers, 1958; 8mm film (Reel 8)
    Parade with Native American dancers, possibly in Gallup, New Mexico.
  - Grand Canyon dwelling, 1958; 8mm film (Reel 9)
    Grand Canyon dwelling, camoes on river (possibly Green River).
  - Explosion on bank, 1958; 8mm film (Reel 10)
    Explosion on bank; boy scouts on river trip.
  - Canoes on Weber River, 1958; 8mm film (Reel 11)
    Canoes on Weber River; little boy at home.
  - Green River trip, 1958; 8mm film (Reel 12)
    Jones Hole, Columbine Hole, scenery (Green River).
  - Family at home, 1958; 8mm film (Reel 13)
    Girls in Mickey Mouse hats play on trampoline, in neighborhood; little boy.
  - Mountains, Yampa River, 1959; 8mm film (Reel 14)
    Mountains, river (possibly Yampa River); Sam.
  - Canoes, rapids, 1959; 8mm film (Reel 15)
    Canoes, rapids; red rock river trip.
  - Glen Canyon river trip, 1961; 8mm film (Reel 16)
    Cliff, Rainbow Bridge; swim.
  - Boy Scouts river trip, 1962; 8mm film (Reel 17)
    Boy scouts river trip – begins on Lewis Bros. Stages bus.
  - River rafting, Native Americans, 1962; 8mm film (Reel 18)
    River rafting; Native Americans on reservation and river.
  - Boy Scouts, ten men, 1962; 8mm film (Reel 19)
    Boy scouts, ten men; San Juan, big hole (river).
  - Chaco Canyon, 1962; 8mm film (Reel 20)
  - San Juan, Grand Canyon, 1962; 8mm film (Reel 21)
  - Cliff, Burra, 1962; 8mm film (Reel 22)
  - San Juan, RT Rinte, 1962; 8mm film (Reel 23)
  - Escalante River trip, 1963; 8mm film (Reel 24)
  - Glen Canyon river trip, 1963; 8mm film (Reel 25)
  - Indian boat, undated; 8mm film (Reel 26)
    Native American boat, canoe on Weber River.
  - River rafting, undated; 8mm film (Reel 27)
    Good shots of 'Moki Mac' himself.
- 16mm films, circa 1914; 1960
  - Glen Canyon, 1960; 16mm film (Reel 28)
    Colorado River, Native American ruins, people climbing on sandstone.
  - San Juan, 1960; 16mm film (Reel 29)
    Native Americans in community, on river trip.
  - Early Colorado River film, circa 1914; 16mm film Black and white, silent (Reel 30)
    Colorado river trip with intertitles.
  - Early Colorado River film, circa 1914; 16mm film Purple tinted, silent (Reel 31)
    Colorado river trip with intertitles. Same as reel 30.